Chirag Gupta, Ph.D.

Postdoctoral Associate Waisman Center, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin, 53705, USA Webpage: cngupta.github.io

Email: chiraggupta.bioinfo@gmail.com

Phone: (479) 799-7136

SUMMARY

Bioinformatics Scientist with 9+ years of experience in plant and human genomics. My objective is to develop bioinformatics solutions for integrating multi-modal data, and applications of machine learning techniques to guide clinical decision making and design efficacious wet lab experiments. I have extensive experience in written and oral communication to academics and business leaders through contributions to winning grants, 10+ peer reviewed publications, 4+ oral and 10+ poster presentations.

EDUCATION

2017	Ph.D. Cell and Molecular Biology Dissertation: Transcriptome-based gene networks for systems-level analysis of gene function in plants	University of Arkansas, Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA
2009	M.Sc. Bioinformatics	Sardar Patel University, India
2007	B.Sc. Bioinformatics	Sardar Patel University, India

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

TEGE/TEGE			
2021 – present	Postdoctoral Research Associate	University of Wisconsin,	
	 Brain-related disorders 	Madison, Wisconsin, USA	
	 Single cell gene regulatory networks 		
	Heterogenous data integration		
2017 – 2020	Postdoctoral Research Associate	University of Arkansas,	
	 Rice environmental stress biology 	Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA	
	Network-based machine learning for	- ,	
	<u> </u>		
	gene prioritization		
	 Web applications (GRAiN) 		
2012 - 2017	Graduate Research Assistant	University of Arkansas,	
	 Plant stress and developmental biology 	Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA	
	 Transcriptomics 		
	 Gene coexpression networks 		
	 Web applications (RECoN, SANe) 		
2008 - 2009	Student Researcher	Disha Life Sciences Pvt. Ltd.,	
	 Fusion proteins in cancer 	Gujarat, India	
	Protein structure prediction	-	
	·		
	 Molecular modeling, drug designing 		

PUBLICATIONS

Under review/preprints

1. **Chirag Gupta**, Arjun Krishnan, Andrew Schneider, Cynthia Denbow, Eva Collakova, Pawel Wolinski, Andy Pereira. SANe: The Seed Active Network for Discovering Transcriptional Regulatory Programs of Seed Development. bioRxiv, doi: 10.1101/165894 (in revision)

In preparation

- 1. Applications of artificial intelligence and machine learning to multimodal data in intellectual and developmental disabilities (*review paper*; 2022)
- 2. Gene regulatory network rewiring in human brain cell types under health and disease conditions (original research; 2022)

Peer reviewed journal articles

- 1. **Chirag Gupta**, Venkategowda Ramegowda, Supratim Basu, Andy Pereira. Using network-based machine learning to predict transcription factors involved in drought stress resistance. *Frontiers in Genetics*, *June 2021.* [full text]
- 2. Raksha Singh, Rohana Liyanage, **Chirag Gupta**, Jackson Lay Jr., Andy Pereira, Clemencia Rojas. The protein interactomes of AtNHR2A and AtNHR2B unraveled common and specialized functions in plant immunity integrating distinct biological processes. *Frontiers in Plant Science*, *March 2020.* [full text]
- 3. Min Woo Lee, Carmen S. Padilla, **Chirag Gupta**, Aravind Galla, Andy Pereira, Jiamei Li, Fiona L. Goggin. The FATTY ACID DESATURASE 2 family in tomato contributes to primary metabolism and stress responses. *Plant Physiology*, *Nov. 2019.* [full text]
- 4. **Chirag Gupta** and Andy Pereira. Recent advances in gene function prediction using context-specific coexpression networks in plants. *F1000Research*, Feb. 2019. [full text]
- 5. Arjun Krishnan, **Chirag Gupta**, Madana MR Ambavaram, Andy Pereira. RECoN: Rice Environment Co-expression Network for systems level analysis of abiotic-stress response. *Frontiers in Plant Science*, Sep. 2017. [full text]
- 6. Venkategowda Ramegowda, Upinder Singh Gill, Palaiyur Nanjappan Sivalingam, Aarti Gupta, **Chirag Gupta**, Geetha Govind, Karaba N Nataraja, Andy Pereira, Makarla Udayakumar, Kirankumar S Mysore, Muthappa Senthil-Kumar. GBF3 transcription factor imparts drought tolerance in Arabidopsis thaliana. *Scientific Reports*, *August 2017*. [full text]
- 7. Venkategowda Ramegowda, Supratim Basu, **Chirag Gupta**, Andy Pereira. Regulation of grain yield in rice under well-watered and drought stress conditions by GUDK. **Plant Signaling and Behavior**, January 2015. [full text]

Published project reports

 Anuj Kumar, Sara Yingling, Yheni Dwiningsih, Charles Ruiz, Julie Thomas, Chirag Gupta, Paul Counce, T.J. Siebenmorgen, Karen AK Moldenhauer, Andy Pereira. Genome-Wide Association Study for Identification of Novel Genomic Loci Associated with Grain Yield and

- Quality Traits in Japonica Rice under High Nighttime Temperature. *B.R. Wells Arkansas Rice Research Studies* 2020, 667:45-48.
- 2. Anuj Kumar, Sara Yingling, Julie Thomas, Charles Ruiz, Yheni Dwiningsih, **Chirag Gupta**, Paul Counce, T.J. Siebenmorgen, Karen A.K. Moldenhauer, Andy Pereira. Screening of Indica and Japonica rice subspecies for grain yield and quality under high nighttime temperature. **B.R. Wells Arkansas Rice Research Studies** 2018, 659:61-66.
- 3. Ramegowda Venkategowda, Subodh Srivastava, Julie Thomas, **Chirag Gupta**, Supratim Basu, Paul Counce, Ya-Jane Wang, Terry Siebenmorgen, Karen Moldenhauer, Andy Pereira. Genetic basis of altered grain quality in different rice cultivars under high nighttime temperature. *B.R. Wells Arkansas Rice Research Studies* 2015, 634:79-85.

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

Talks

- Predicting rice genes important for drought tolerance using gene regulatory networks and machine learning. Crops InSilico, 4th Annual Symposium and Hackathon, Urbana, IL, 3rd May 2019
- Arabidopsis seed-filling association-network analysis. **American Society of Plant Biologists Southern Section (ASPB-SS)**, Lexington, KY, 30th March 2014.

Select posters

- Network-based approach to prioritize lung cancer genes from whole-exome sequencing data. AR-BIC, Little Rock, AR, 25th March 2018
- Differential Co-expression: A new paradigm for identification of candidate genes from expression data. **AR-BIC**, Little Rock, AR, 24th April 2017
- An abiotic-stress conditioned gene regulatory network in rice predicted using an ensemble of reverse-engineering solutions. The 25th Plant and Animal Genome (PAG) Conference, San Diego, CA, 14th January 2017
- A resource for systems analysis of stress response in rice. NSF Workshop on plant development and drought stress, Monterey, CA, 8th November 2015
- StarchNet: Implications of high night-time temperature on starch metabolism regulatory networks in rice. **AR NSF EPSCoR Annual Meeting**, Fayetteville, AR, 15th September 2015
- In Silico Analysis of Fusion Proteins in Cancer, International Conference on Biomedical and Genomic Research, Ahmedabad, India, 30th January 2009

AWARDS

- 1. Crops in silico underrepresented minority travel scholarship, **Crops InSilico**, Urbana, IL, 2019
- 2. Scherago International Student Travel Grants Awards, **The 25th annual Plant and Animal Genome (PAG) meeting**, San Diego, CA, 2017
- 3. NSF Travel Grant to attend the Workshop on Plant Development and Drought Stress, **National Science Foundation**, 2015
- 4. Stood 3rd in merit list for all India entrance examination for Master's in bioinformatics program, **Sardar Patel University**, India, 2007
- 5. 2nd Prize in undergraduate oral presentation, Sardar Patel University, India, 2006
- 6. 3rd Prize in undergraduate poster competition, Atmiya University, India, 2006

GRANT CONTRIBUTIONS

• NSF EPSCoR RII Track-2 FEC 1826836: Systems genetics studies on rice genomes for analysis of grain yield and quality under heat stress (PI: Dr. Andy Pereira; \$4,659,406), 2018

• **NSF MCB 1716844**: Systems genetics analysis of photosynthetic carbon metabolism in rice (PI: Dr. Andy Pereira; \$798,725.00), 2017

SOCIETY MEMBERSHIPS

2019 - present The International Society for Computational Biology (ISCB)

SELECT SKILLS

Programming R, Perl, Shiny, PHP, mySQL

Bioinformatics RNA-seq (single-cell, bulk), ChIP-seq, network modeling, DNA variant

detection, microarrays, GWAS

Workflows Docker, STAR, Tuxedo suite, BWA, Samtools, GATK, Picard, VarScan,

Mutect, SomaticSniper, VCFtools, edgeR, DESeq, limma, LibSVM, Weka,

BLAST, Arguslab, MolSoft, Rasmol, I-TASSER etc.

Visualization R, CytoscapeWeb, D3.js Platforms UNIX, Linux, Google cloud

Tools Developed

GRAiN http://rrn.uark.edu/shiny/apps/GRAiN/
SANe https://plantstress-pereira.uark.edu/SANe/
RECoN https://plantstress-pereira.uark.edu/RECoN/

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Co-taught Plant Genomics (**Bioinformatics/Genomics modules**: CSES 5543, Uni. Of Arkansas), 2016, 2018

EXTENSION ACTIVITIES

Student and Teacher Workshop: rice genetic variation (18 credit hours, Uni. Of Arkansas), 2019

ACADEMIC SERVICE

- Manuscript reviewer for Plant Physiology, Frontiers in Plant Science, Nature Scientific Reports, Rice, Plant Cell Reports, Horticultural Plant Journal, Plant Methods, PLoS One
- Plante Fellow 2019: Contribution to the Plantae online portal for Bioinformatics resources relevant to plant biology research
- Member of the panel of judges for the Northwest Arkansas Regional Science and Engineering Fair 2015,16
- Conducted several training material and hands-on activities for undergraduates and K-12 students from the Arkansas agricultural areas in the Delta region for a STEM literacy outreach program

REFREES

Available upon request